Finding Aid for Alpha Rho Chi (Fraternity) Iktinos Chapter records, 1909-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alpha Rho Chi (Fraternity) Iktions Chapter records 1909-1993
Alpha Rho Chi (fraternity). Iktinos chapter (University of Michigan).
2.5 linear ft. and 1 oversize folder
90167 Bimu 41; UBImum F41
University of Michigan chapter of an architecture student fraternity. Minutes, 1909-1931, of Architectural Society, a University of Michigan group; minutes, newsletters, and other materials of Iktinos Chapter of Alpha Rho Chi; and collected material relating to activities of national office.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 7537 ) was received in March 1988. Additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open for research.
Alpha Rho Chi is a national professional fraternity limiting its membership to students of architecture and the allied arts. It was founded at the Universities of Illinois and Michigan in April 1914, with the intent of enhancing and promoting the artistic, scientific, and practical development of younger members of the architectural profession.
The Iktinos chapter at the University of Michigan has long been active on local and national levels in pursuing this goal. Locally, they have sponsored numerous social activities, as well as educational lectures by notable professional architects. Nationally, members have played an active role in the fraternity's national conventions, and in alumni relations. Some of the records in the collection were damaged by water during a fire at the fraternity's Ann Arbor house in 1938.
The records of the Iktinos Chapter of the Alpha Rho Chi Professional Architectural Fraternity comprise four series: Architectural Society (1909-1931) and Alpha Rho Chi (1914-1993), Photographs, and Sound Recordings. Within each subgroup, files are arranged alphabetically.
Subjects:
Alpha Rho Chi (Fraternity). |b Iktinos Chapter (University of Michigan).; University of Michigan Architectural Society.; University of Michigan |x Students |x Societies, etc.; Architecture.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alpha Rho Chi (Fraternity).-Iktinos Chapter (University of Michigan).; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan--Buildings.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Architectural Society
  The Architectural Society series (0.1 linear ft.) consists of the minutes of the society, a University of Michigan organization formed in 1909 and active until 1931. The minutes indicate that the focus of the society's activity was social. However, in addition to sponsoring dances, they appear to have also sponsored lectures by faculty members.
  - Architectural Society minutes, 1909-1931, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Alpha Rho Chi
  The records of the Alpha Rho Chi series (1.9 linear ft.) contain almost equal parts local and national records. Included are extensive chapter minutes, covering social activities and lectures. Also included is the chapter newsletter, which includes announcements of activities as well as news about alumni. The "Guest Books" provide a glimpse of what specific activities took place, and who attended. The "House Fund" file contains an interesting entry regarding the chapter's acquisition of their own house in 1922. The national records include an almost complete run of the national magazine. Subjects covered include activities of active members and alumni and events at universities. The "Reports of the Annual National Convention" (.5 linear ft.) give an excellent view of the fraternity's goals and achievements at the national and chapter levels.
  - "Archi" (national magazine), 1918-1986, 5 folders; (incomplete) (Box 1)
  - Grand Council of Alpha Rho Chi Financial Reports, 1956-1970 (Box 1)
  - Guest Books (bound), 1919-1965, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - House Fund, 1919-1922 (Box 1)
  - "Iktinews" chapter newsletter (incomplete), 1948-1993 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1914-1971
    - 1914-May 1948, 5 folders (Box 1)
      (gap from 1928 to 1937)
    - September 1948-May 1971, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Pledge Manuals (Box 2)
    (? to 10/80)
  - Reports of the Annual National Convention (1st to 34th), 1915-1972, 10 folders (Box 2)
    (missing 26th, 30th and 33rd annual conventions)
  - Financial Records (includes membership dues), 1913-1915 (2 bound volumes) (Box 2)
  - Collected materials from individual members
    - Bert Trowell file (miscellaneous materials) (Box 3)
    - Amy Reineri file (miscellaneous materials) (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includeds photos of fraternity members, the Alpha Rho Chi house and various socal activities.
  - Fraternity house (Box 3)
  - Group portraits (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Social activities (Box 3)
  - Various groupings (Box 3)
- Sound recording
  - Bertil Lindblad tape discussing in part the history of APX for 1936-1940, 1 sound cassette (Box 3)
    (mainly music of the period and U-M Glee Club)